hello and welcome everyone it's October
18th
2023 we're in the course active
inference for the social sciences and
today we're in the lecture by the course
co-organizer and that will kick off the
final leg of the course which is AAL
gwiin Caro's lecture social constraints
and the existential
what makes us human so we'll be looking
forward to a lecture followed by a
discussion so if you have any questions
please feel free to add them in the live
chat or submit to the course syllabus
and also at the end we'll talk about how
we're going to conclude this course so
with that thank you to you
evil Hello uh sir do you see the slides
correctly everything is
fine
I will take sence as a
yes uh so uh the the role of this
session is basically to uh to show you
the inspiring intuition behind the all
course and to show very concretely well
very abstractly but in my mind
concretely why the specific formalism of
active inference and social constraints
is relevant to understand the human
species and the stult evolution of you
know things that we do
so we'll talk of uh social constraints
of the exist of the existential stance
and of what makes us human so disclaimer
uh this paper this presentation is
closely aligned with upcoming paper
which whose name is like the same I
think is tentative for now and whose
cter whose man on job is a
c
so uh first let us ask basic questions
about the topic at hand what is is
culture uh by psychologist sesa uh
culture is typically used in one of
three way culture can be information or
behavior required socially so like if I
am an ant and I figure out that you need
to go somewhere because
of feromon this is culture it can be
social equate behavior that is shared
within a group uh so for example if I am
a nape and I figure out how to open nuts
with a stone thing
and the group just everyone does it the
same way this is culture and it can be
the Adaptive evolution of socially
acquired behavior which is uh like fam
well we have evidence of of it in the in
in the wild for corvids and humans
only so um the question is we know that
culture is the human specific like it's
it it it is the case simply but
depending on what we mean by culture it
can entail it can describe behavior that
is much very much
shared um with other species so the
question a question that need to be
answered is how specific are uh the
human cultural
mechanisms so um One Core thing to
understand is that there is no such
thing as the cultural mechanism the
mechanisms of learning in humans they
are uh culturally transmitted whether
you will listen to I don't know
Elder uh rapper um scientist depends on
the cultural norms in which you
exists and the specific way in which uh
teacher student interaction are supposed
to go is again culturally
embedded and the type of information
that people will try to figure out is or
transmit is itself Cur embedded so we
can just write the mechanism for human
social learning this is like empirically
there is known and conceptually I would
don't I don't think the notion is
coherent to begin
with um so one core argument for this is
We have basically um explicit linguistic
rules about we who we should trust like
listen to your
parents and those are linguistic and
language varies from culture to culture
so this changes from culture to culture
pretty
straightforward and in general the uh
practice of cultural submission of
intentional teaching they uh they are
varying between cultures and I do not
want to get into it because I don't
think I would say something that is
accurate without
notes and um we can however take a look
at take a look at a behavior that is I
think nearly Universal which is
storytelling when people uh tell
story they use stories to transmit norms
and uh like in the specific uh culture
of the a or AKA I I I have misspelled it
at least once I think it is agda like
you have a like core role of
Storytelling in telling people what to
do and you have specific
uh tales that were studied and that were
assciated to specific
norms and these are very important
because like here we have laws that are
written somewhere and that like people
in blue will come and hit you if you
don't follow them but this is not
something that is reveral so in a
context where you do not have States you
typically have no really other way to
transmit Norms than you know talk about
it uh
and so from there everything is citt
like the way the Norms the kind of norms
can be transmitted given this way uh the
way specific cues will be understood
given specific Niche ET Etc so yes all
this to say there is no Big C culture
there is cultural transmission there is
cultural Evolution but there is no
specific mechanism or um you know
natural type of culture in
humans but
uh there are uh categories of behavior
that are very obviously human specifics
and that are very obviously cultural as
in direct
contribution to culture for example fire
it's obviously majorly important to
culture because if you have fire you get
a lot of calories if you get a lot of
calories you get a big brain like can
four brain but fire you know doesn't
produce culture that's not how anything
Works uh things that do work directly PR
culture are language and Ro taking so
language I think you are familiar with
it you are using it now on the receiving
side it is a practice that basically
embeds communicative intents into a
specific set of symbols that can be
letters that can be words like or it
would be phun I guess I don't know the
Phim or the word is a symbol but you
have symbols and I Amed meaning and
people use it and what is critical is
that each of these
symbol has a public meaning has a public
like semantics and pragmatics if I tell
you
chair maybe we don't know precisely uh
like what specific thing enters in the
chair category maybe
perceptual insation of chair will vary
but like we are we agree on the basics
of the chair we agree on what we can do
with chairs we agree with a lot of thing
implicitly by the use of this word and
we can use the of syntax to manipulate
this unit of meaning in a specific way I
sit on a chair I'm talking an action
that is relative to a specific object
that is a chair and you understand what
I mean if I was trying to you know mic
it maybe I get it through maybe you
would think I'm saying I'm crotching
over uh bad what why
not and so the language and the fact
that it has a publically instanciated
meaning is critical in you know keeping
a coordination in the specific thing
that people do and why they do it which
is unambigously cultural and you have
another more subtle mechanism uh process
I don't know phenomenon which is uh
shared intentionality so by the work of
mainly tomasel we know that uh chimps
are not very
social and they can learn they are but
as intelligent as
humans but at least young humans but
they usually are not really interested
in what other CHS are doing and most
importantly they are not interested in
um like sharing goals trying to figure
out what is the end result that some
other chimp is upholding and trying to
like mesh in this plan to help him while
in human from a very young age we are
very exem
motivated and we are very motivated to
like figure out what we whatever we is
are collectively doing
and figure out what one's role is in
that and do that and this is likely not
you know a bona cognitive function that
stands on its own but it's a behavior
that is a cognitive process that is
anemic in
humans very rare if existing everywhere
else and that is core to most theory of
the of culture so these two things we
know are human specifics up to maybe
very small important details and we know
are critically embedded in what we call
culture and so what I will do uh from
now on is to provide a specific theory
of culture so the active inference of
cultural
landscapes that in my
opinion basically explains or at least
um meshes well
with why those two specific phenomenons
are so important from the apping of
culture but it also means that culture
is not information pery it's something
that is more organic and that
evolves more like you know biological
system themselves evolve than population
of gen and from these accounts we will
go to um figure out what it means about
Collective organization uh figure out
what why we have gods and
taxes and from there we will go to a
more physical and pcal consideration and
ask how basically this Theory can be
written within physics uh through the
active inference
formalism so let us
go uh first I'm just presenting the
theory of the active inference of clear
landscape and I presenting a core
concept the concept of C constraints
that there from at least my treatment of
that so active INF frence uh probably a
lot of you know what this is but this
goes on YouTube so I will re explain
active inference is a theory of
cognition where basically agents enact
expectation of the world they have a
world model and they make predictions
over the world model and they strive for
those predictions to remain coherent
with what they actually observe and that
means that the agent will you know
update beliefs that are false if I uh
hear moow and I think there is no
Cuts I will then think that it is more
likely that and on the other hand I will
try to provoke to like realize uh
prediction that I can of need so for
example if I uh really want to hear Mo
if I really expect to hear moo and I
expect this to be like
a basic steple of my life I will maybe
figure out how to get a cats that works
not well with cats but with drinking or
eating yeah expect to be a thing that
has water in it because else I die so
when I'm thirsty I am Thirst by drinking
and you have this basically duality of
productive like normal what we call
typically perception just trying to
figure out what there is outside and
updating our belief when we don't so I
said perception but is more in inference
and there is active inference which is
uh like the realization of this
inference through action and a
core argument of active inference is
that those two are uh same process they
are the same process that is entailed by
an information geometry so basically a
space of belief over which the Dynamics
of an agent uh
unfold and the core feature of the this
approach is uh the dissolution of agency
as we typically understand it we
typically understand agency to be like
hey I'm an agent I want to do this and I
will reason about what I want and I will
reason about how to get it and will do
the thing that I reasoned
about reason is important it's not the
basic cognitive function that analyze
everything we do I do not think the
statement is controversal
IAL and in active inference the model we
have is that like at multiple scale in
multiple context we like again produce
prediction over our sensor flow and then
strive to realize those prediction so
what that means is that direction are
not constrained by
will uh in the Jal case they're
constrained by what looks more like a
self model a model of on self and what
on self would typically do in text such
as as the one I'm exposed
to
um related concept is the notion of
skill and intentionality so this is this
uh skill intentionality thing is a
theory that stands at the interface
between active inference and ecological
psychology which I will absolutely not
get
into and the core argument of skill
intentionality is that when you are a
skilled agent so agents that you know
understand how to do things in the
world you do not experience the world as
a like uh represented space in 3D with
uh 3D models in it and each object is
well defined and a lot of has a lot of
properties that are embedded in a world
model that like you have in a video game
uh what you see is a landscape of basic
opportunities for I will see a computer
I know I can mash the keys keys I think
you say keys and I know I can go to the
internet and I know I can do this or
that I see a door I know I can go
through it if it's open I can close it I
can go through it if it's closed and I
can open it this is the basic
opportunities that the door
present and um we don't say a logical
consequence but uh very
coherent uh entailment active inference
is that I will see minimal model of
things around me that are based on the
opportunities for Action that they
present I will Orient my attention
minimally to grasp what I can do with
things and what the field perceptive
field that I live in is a landscape of
those aford
denes so the um picture is an extract
from Fallout New Vegas which is the gr
RPG please play it this is important
only thing you need to keep in mind on
this course and that shows you like a
radio in like 3DF of radio and you have
an action button that tells you whether
you want to activate the radio and you
have HPS and APS I have no idea what AP
is and this looks more like a naive
field than what you get into um really
realistic presentation of like a a
picture photo picture of your
environment because you have the
perception of the uh object like you
have a TOD array that presents you know
your vision of an object but it's
embedded in things that tell you where
you're looking at things that tell you
what you can do with things things that
tell you what are your States what are
your basic state when you're engaging
with this uh object and this is uh I
think pretty
nice uh
illustr
of what we could mean by perception and
the landscape ised you need
LS sorry a could you repeat the last 30
seconds there it was just like it hung
up okay just just repeat the last 30
seconds thank you so this is a picture
from Fallout New Vegas which is a good
game and I claim that it is a pretty
good illustration of what we talk when
we talk about ACC related perception
because you see the object and with
slash through the object you also see
what opportunities for Action it
presents in this case activate the radio
and you see it in the way is embedded
with your pH physiological States so the
HP and AP
and a
core feature of that is that uh when I
experence
affordances I feel directly through the
perception whether the affordance is
good or
bad uh if I see I don't know um a cliff
and I I can fall off the cliff and die
uh this will cause Fair the perception
of that possibility of falling and dying
will be negatively loaded if I see I
don't know a hot bed in Winter and I
know I can now rest after a day of work
where I was cold I will be happy about
it I will perceive the possibility in a
like positively balanced way and so this
is the case for like basic phys
physiological thing but this is also the
case for cultural norms and values we
come to experience the world as a world
of affordances and and this is the same
for the social world I will feel bad or
good depending on what possibility for
Action I will experience in a given
context and
um this is a picture of forest path near
archical site that is um that is studied
by the research group that funds me
escape and like from a pure direct
perception kind of way there is like uh
very complex statistical feature that
are made in the picture but if you are a
human a thing that walks what you will
perceive like feel directly experience
directly is just a possibility to walk
along the path and follow it and this is
something that you feel is a property of
the path I think you see a path you
think I can go through a path you don't
think there is a 3D space and in this 3D
space there is a set of statistical
feature one of which being a flat thing
in the middle and among the enter space
of action that they have one of them is
to walk through the path like just do
this and this and this and this you just
feel like you can go through
there and uh the way humans uh learn
about each other uh the way humans
citate and uh come to expect things
about each other uh they can develop
basically a sense of what is cultural
possible or not possible in a given
context and this uh sensation this
perception of cultural
possibilities it is embedded in the way
we pay attention to things we will pay
attention to different things according
to like you know what is culturally rent
in a given context in a given situation
and this is a core argument of the um
thinking through the minds account of
cultural Evolution which was uh
spearheaded by Maxwell rad and um this
year forgot uh his first
name and because of everything that we
saw before because of the dissolved
agency that we have under active in
France the patterns cultural patterns in
the FL of attention they will not simply
be experienced as you know like abstract
norms and value that one could or could
not respect they will effectively
constrain the thing you can pay
attention to the outcome you expect in a
way that will um Drive Your Action
toward specific outcomes and so this
cultural landscape of
affordances they embed
intivity as in the patterns that are
relevant to explain normativity and
intentionality they are in the landscape
they are not like only at least in your
brain
cells and a core argument I would say is
that uh the engagement with a cultural
landscape it is D to existence of social
constraints where cir constraints are
understood as statistical patterns that
will like causally act over what you do
or cannot do so when I talk about the
Str landscape of fores I am implicitly
talking about a set of constraints that
ta over behavior and this I've
demonstrated by talking about Med
Nativity and the
like
um you have uh how to
say you have added Nuance in the uh
notion of constraints which is
that
a
sorry
again AVL from your side is just I'm not
hearing any
audio ma or Maria do you hear him no
nothing you can't write over Collective
Behavior so there is scale of one
specifications yes all right could you
repeat could you repeat the last 45
seconds can you hear me now
yeah
okay so what I'm saying is that the
engagement with cultural landscape
parenes it is dual to the existence of
sh constraints which act over individual
Behavior because when I engage
individually with the landscape fenes
that is a characteristic of my local
material and cural
environments uh the like tivity will
drive my behavior my intention my
presentation in a specific way and
instead of looking at how each
individual agent engage with the
landscape I can look at the constraints
that emerge from this uh Collective
activity so is that do you hear me
now okay yeah
yeah okay
good and uh so let us get back to the uh
question of what makes us human uh we
had talked about human specific uh
mechanism phenomenon that seem to be
involved in culture those were language
and Ro taking and those two phenomenons
seem to be pretty robust um candidate to
explain the coherence of a shared
cultureal landscape or set of SL
constraints uh language it provides a
space of Public Presentation like
representation in the classical ctiv
sense that you can negotiate that are
actually out there in the literal sense
they are sensory signals that are in the
environment and that uh structure agent
Behavior so when you talk to yourself it
will constrain what you pay attention to
implicitly what you can and cannot do
and when you talk with others this will
you know influence what you say and what
you want to say and what you perceive to
be R to say and so it will constrain
your behavior and in a much stronger and
more robust way than you could have to
implicit intentionality
inference and Ro taking in a more subtle
way uh brings agent to think
existentially to like not ask the
question what I I am supposed to do in
the situation but what an agent that is
embedded in the specific cultural
context where I embedded is expected to
do and so this basically forces you to
um have a synchronization between what
you experience as possibilities for
action and what you expect our cultural
expectation over Behavior so these two
mechanisms there would be very very
strong uh mechanisms to enforce the
coherence of cognitive landscape between
agents and it just happens that there
are things that exist only in the one
spey that has full-fledged cumulative
open-ended cultural
Evolution so yes I think this is uh
interesting okay
a you just unshared your
screen sorry you unshared your screen or
is that
done uh no I did not un my
screen hm could you just like reshare
it yes there you go all right all right
looks great continue thank
you nice um so yes the question is
um as I said there is a duality between
each agent engaging with a landscape for
dance and uh constraints that exist over
the landscape that is shared that is
straightforward but
uh in the set of constraints that is um
characteristic of a given
landscape uh basically to ACC for p
culture Evolution this must be a set of
constraints that uh changes through time
that builds new constraints and New Deal
flow and it's something that you cannot
get with a landscape in the uh sense of
deal System Theory that is not Nial
System Theory does not deal with systems
that do aand Devol
so the question is what relation can we
make between the Dynamics of
enculturation according to each agent
integrate specific cultural expectation
and the Dynamics of open ended cultur
Evolution through which cultural
landscape and the
constraints um like constructs itself
through
time and this is where we get to the
more holistic side where uh I think we
can see why the specific construct of
constraints is a critical as compared to
the simple cultureal landscape approach
let us take a look at
this there is a thing CA called
biological autonomy it is a quite recent
term in its formalization the relevant
formalization that describes the ability
of a living system for self-
construction like maintaining one
structor and changing it through
Developmental and evolutionary time and
the best formalization we have that so
far is from Mon and
and it's a constraint closure a con
constraint is simply a relatively slow
physical process that shapes a faster
process like canaly material or
information or energy flow without
itself being affected dur at the time
scale of the
interaction and for mosio you get
biological autonomy where you get a set
of constraints that collectively produce
itself each constraint constraints is
produced by other constraints in the set
and each constraint produces other
constraints in the set this is a very
simple ID this is a very informal ID in
a sense that it is not doesn't have
Dynamics doesn't have a physics it is
just a formal statement of what we mean
by
autonomy and
this uh I basically is the best
grounding we have to think about what is
living and what is an agent although in
itself it does not entail
agency and uh when we look at Social
systems or systems as a set of
constraints um what you can see is that
system such as the brain multiscale
organized system they can be read as
basically a set of n constraints like
your uh dmn the activity of your um
default mode Network which is the basal
activity of the brain in the absence of
stimulation it's uh basically is consed
of dial constraints over what the
composant um tissues do at a given point
in time and this itself is a constraint
over what individual cells do uh through
time which itself is a constraint over
the evolution law of an individual cell
etc etc etc so I can always look at a m
scale system as a set of nested
constraints at Ned
scales and in systems that are um
autonomous that are biological cognitive
agent um not only the um smaller scale
uh systems like cell they can uh they
enable they construct and they enact the
constraints that are AOS scale
agents but ioscale agents can also shape
back the behavior of low scale agent
like of course if I have you know if I
do something which is something that I
as an agent do this will constrain my
the activity of my neuron networks this
is like heavan learning this is common
to all model of learning learning goes
through change in network
structure and so there is an opportunity
to model uh
emerging agent from like Collective
network activity and to look to look at
interaction between description at Ned
scales of
behavior and uh this is applicable very
fly to the human species so this is a
suy
States and something that you can look
look is that uh it is very dense it has
very dense building that are buil in a
specific way it is near a
river uh which enables the um trade at
Great distance it has a bridge so entry
to the city is constrained to a specific
point and it is essentially surrounded
by several Fields very flat lands that
are Rubble that are um fertilized
probably by uh water from the
river and basically all of these feature
are enable the production of a state
societies societies with a central
Administration that does stuff and these
societies will mostly produce context uh
material context that faize their own
Survival for example then settlements
enable you to like have everyone
together to tell them what to do temples
which give a matal grounding to the
authority of the states uh bridges that
allow you to move things around and to
control what gets in and out and more
cultural seral fields that allow you to
like take the food and bring it back to
the
city and the prod ction of such
settlements and such material
environment by States is uh somewhat
robust Intercultural
Fon uh at more
like ancient are a multicultural scale
um you have a set of process that are
critical in the construction and action
of norms in humans and most likely
common Anor to to those processes is
dancing and singing dancing and singing
that they give you um like embodied
synchronization and this is shown to
drive development of group identity and
this gives you basically emotional
grounding of the Norms that are shared
within Society because they those Norms
they are not abstract expectation they
are uh embedded in your specific
emotions in your specific embodiment
while you do things that are uh critical
to your
ecology and ritual activity and
storytelling they allow uh more complex
storativity by using you know
symbolism and the system of toity that
are maybe less embedded embodied sorry
so less embedded in the uh like
On's direct experience but they allow a
more more complexity in the nature of
the Norms that are transmitted and
enforced and uh the these
Norms the by the simple fact that they
are perceptible through matal symbolism
and through storytelling they become a
causal force in the cultural landscape
in the that is shared by a group member
so they become thing that are uh the
power to produce or constraint the
framing in which people will read
specific situation and therefore
constrain and produce s
behavior and this
um this is like I've said this already
so this looks like repetition but I want
to hammer this because if this is the
case uh then we can be interested in
what complex uh
tals in so sorry in agency that emerges
from the constraints embedded in complex
Tales so we know that uh people can
perceive nonmaterial agents under
certain conditions uh this is common in
schizophrenia like you will hear voices
that tells you to do things and that are
not embedded in a specific body this
come on in a deive Valen disorder
because you will have agents that
basically share your body while while
having an existing while not being tied
to a specific uh body
like one sorry I'm misspeaking one
specific personality can exist while
they're not in control of your body and
so in a way that is is not contingent on
the direct matal inaction of what they
want and want not to do and under a lot
of anthrop anthropologically um
described
conditions uh that are not considered
pathological you can basically have
regimes of attention that produce a
normous agent that you can talk with and
that have motivation and that have
traits which are often called tpas uh
which is term borrowed from Buddhist
literature and uh so
this emergence of the material
agent how to say if I consider an agent
to be something a closed set of
constraints and I consider things like
tail and ritual as mechanism that
produce constraints in Behavior there is
basically no difficulty whatsoever at
concept level there is is no
unexpectedness or no complexity to say
that uh specific systems of constraint
that happen to be closed and that are
embeded in those tales and rituals they
exist as biological
agent and uh so we can have basically a
model of gods of nonmaterial Agents
which is a better less loaded way to put
it that relies on a systematic training
of your regime of attention and of
course uh when it's Collective it will
like those agents will be social agent
there will be things that have uh Power
that have the ability to frame the
debate on specific things if you and I
think that uh so this is sorry the
painting that is on the right of the
screen is a painting by William Blake
that presents uh basically a late 18th I
think nation of God which is um not
really old testament which is a bit more
New Testament but which is mostly in
sensation of the um clock maker God that
was popular at the time and what you see
uh on the painting isan So William
Blake's version of God that is in the
sky like very powerful very Z like
imagery and that is using um like this
his hand to draw a compass that is
considered a symbol of like um
constructing things of masonry like the
compass is one of the Freemason uh
symbol for the same reason it is a
symbol of orderly Creation in Willam
Blake's uh paintings and so if we share
a belief that there is a God somewhere
and he build the world as it is
intentionally and this God is benevolent
or at least much too powerful for us to
fight with basically your option they B
on to following the order because if you
don't God will remove you from the order
and you don't want that do you so even
if you don't have uh the existence of
like um
matal a materal sensation of this God
even if people don't really really
believe that there is actually a guy
with a bird that does
stuff uh they sh ritualized uh belief in
an entity that has this specific
motivation and the specific traits it
will uh shape heavily the social
landscape that is avable to everyone and
this is
compatible with um aloid does not entail
the existence of actual agency that is
tied to this specific entity through the
constraints that this entity concretely
is and something that I find again
interesting is that religion that are
popular today so Christianity Islam
Buddhism
Hinduism if you think of something as a
religion will likely fall under
this this um handle are typically what
White House called doctrinal religion
which are religion that are where
basically you sit down and you look at
rituals and there is uh priesthood that
is trained to do the ritual in a
specific way that is supposed to mean
specific things and this is basically
optimal to build very robust Notions of
uh what gods are what they want from you
what they do what they are motivated by
etc
so I must insist that this is with a
question mark But in principle the um
the social constraints model it can
produce an theistic theory of gods and
nonmaterial agent sorry as socially
embedded nonmaterial agent that are
computed
uh collectively through engagement with
a specific cultural landscape where uh
ritual and doctrinal
um
elaboration are are important
components and I can say with
exclamation mark that this model it
enables naturalistic theory of social
agency that is not tied specifically to
individual bodies if I consider a social
system actual organization to be
autonomous that is closed system of
constraints uh then agency or maybe um
non-trial agency it simply reduces to
the power to shape sorry shape this uh
landscape and you can have uh emergent
social things do that you can have
states which follow specific rules so
social constraints and specific Norms so
G constraints that have autonomy and
that are able to shape the
landscape but in all of this like this
part in my opinion uh
shows
that c constraints specifically are
relevant to study the social worlds that
they correspond
[Music]
to relevant social process in human
other agents that are institutions and
maybe again question mark materal agents
sorry agent institution so
Gods uh the question that needs to be
asked is how we can model the portion of
constraints because all of these rely on
the IDE that somehow in the landscape
that we experience there is such a thing
as constraints and they are well defined
thing that exist over Collective
behavior and that they have the pro the
property to construct
itself and for reason we'll very shortly
see to frame this mathematically in a
coherent way is insanely hard I don't
know how to do it no one knows how to do
it we have leads but they are leads
nothing else and so we'll turn to the
question of uh whether active inference
frames a gge theory for inculturation
ination you should know what this is by
now go Theory we will see that soon
so to explain gge Theory I need to
explain explanation which is fun but
mostly symmetries uh in physics in
physics uh we frame physical problem
around
symmetries symmetry it is a algebraic so
something that has composition like plus
groups of transformation over the space
of
possibilities which are irrelevant from
the perspective of the same Dynamics is
very struct so let's look at
symmetries this is the ceiling of the
Lola mos in found what you can see is a
symmetry under the C 32 symmetry group
if you shift this picture by um one over
32 uh full turn it does not change this
is what we mean by a symmetry this is a
transformation a set of transformation
that is
closed and that does not change well not
a picture of course in the context of
physics
but uh the Dynamics of the relevant
system we are
studying and for formal reasons I will
not absolutely not get into here
explanation in physics it usually
derives from the statement of symmetry
for example when I state that energy is
conserved this is the same formally
stating that my system is symmetric in
time when I state that momentum is
conserved that radius formally uh to
stating that my system is a symmetric in
space okay so most things in physics can
be framed as simply symmetries over
System
Dynamics and a gge theory is simply uh
elaborate instance of this core
ID so if your symmetry is uh has two
properties first it is continuous so not
like the uh a set of small rotation but
like the set of all possible rotation
that you can take uh around the circle
and local so you can apply the Symmetry
transformation to every single point is
space uh your problem basically can be
framed with the real degree of Freedom
so because of the symmetry does not
change a system whether your system
where your system is in the for example
Clockwork rotation it is not important
it does not change the
dyamics uh so this R degree of Freedom
we call a gge parameter
um the core feature of gge theory is to
take the geometry of that problem and
make it into a physical Force so um when
I say uh G parameter so this is um you
should see in the in the
screen uh non-trivial Z of a two Z
princial bundle of a ccle which means
basically that you have a circle it has
two stages and when you are over it you
can be either on top or down and you
can't know where it is so this is a not
quite to the gra freedom because you
have only two choices to get to the gra
Freedom you have to get a continuous
space of choices but this is basically
what we mean by gge parameter it is a
geometric property of your system that
you know mathematically exist but that
cannot possibly be observed
or how to say corresponds to a choice in
how you absorb your system so this is
why we talk of G because this is a
choice in how weend the system but I
will not get into the details of this
here and the thing is that because of
its redundancy The Gorge parameter does
not have to be the same in a specific
trajectory uh at any given point in
space and from that you get curvature
and curvature if you are are anywhere in
physics and you
know
a okay last thing we heard was if you're
anywhere in physics know about
relativity Theory you will know that to
the like naive embeding space so if you
know uh vaguely Theory you know yes
sorry just if you're anywhere physics
and then continue from there
yes so if you are Vaguely Familiar with
relativity Theory you know that
curvature in a space it corresponds to
forces so in relativity Theory the
curvature of SpaceTime it corresponds to
uh the gravity force and generally in uh
physics the curvature in other weirder
gge spaces it translates in the other
FAL for so weak Force strong force and
um
electromagnetism so yes just stating
that there is a
space which has a Gorge parameter in it
and this space has a curvature it
entails that you have a force that
emerges over the let us say natural
framing of the
problem and uh this uh speaks very
closely to activ
inference so active inference can be
framed as a consequence of a formal
result that is called the principle let
us uh write a dial system stochastic
which means that it has noise in it and
which can be a partition between an
agent a environment b and a boundary
sorry an environment E and A boundary B
such that the distribution of of the
agent and the adment are independent
from each other uh given the dispostion
of the boundary B which kind of means
that any
information uh in E that is relevant in
a and vice versa has to be in B but
doesn't quite mean that but it's very
close uh then you have a information
geometry which is uh like geometrical
construct where each point in the agent
corresponds to dision of belief over uh
the space of external
States and because of this information
geometry each possible internal state of
the agent it entails implicitly a belief
over exteral States so this means that
given a condition of partition
ability uh I can write basian belief
over my environment as a simple
geometrical property of the space we are
uh working in and as I just said when
you have a geometry and it's curved you
get
forces and
so uh the F can
straightforwardly be framed as a go
Theory where the Symmetry is in sensory
entropy technically but let us say the
space of belief I am evolving in
directly constrain my action in a
specific manner to constrain basian
coherence between what I expect to be
the case and what I experience to be the
case and so straightforwardly this
grounds active inference because like
what I just said is what I said to
explain active inference up to some
technical words that were added in but
yes this result entails uh predictive
processing and predictive control of
behavior of the agent and to some extent
impr proves the possibility of this
existing in bare uh demicol systems
Theory but I do not think that the FP
can possibly represent
enculturation so when I talk of AAL
system this is a system with Dynamics in
it you are I think you understand
that I do not think you understand the
formalism that we imply by
ital system is a flow function Fe a Time
parameter T and State Space X so what
that means is that to frame an equal
system I have to write a space let us
say I don't know just the Olan space
with three dimension I have to specify
time which is like naturally in the CLE
space what we think of as time and I
have to specify a specific way in which
the um my system will move in space in a
given uh step of time so fig gives from
any position and any time slot where the
system will be if it starts from this
position after the specific time
duration this like this is what AAL
system is but if you have
noticed this uh this entails that I
Define preemptively all of the space of
possibilities of my
system if I have a system that is a you
know open-ended system of constraints
that can build new stuff that can build
language that can build accounting
whatever new States this doesn't go
maybe you say uh We Could reconstruct a
minimal motion of new stuff Happening by
work sorry I'll ask him
again
a again repeat the last 30
seconds
but your audio is still not there it's
like a 30 to 40 second period where
you're audio just doesn't transmit none
of us can hear
it but the internet is
fineing over the dyamics of the system
per in system the so you can do that EI
so yeah
continue yep continue
okay so uh let me system can be written
as a flow function Fe over a state Space
X and A Time parameter
t uh when you specify X you specify the
total space of possibility of the system
so if you have a system that has openend
evolution in it well you cannot work
with a fixed space you could maybe uh
like circum the issue by implicitly
having new things happen from a change
in the Dynamics of the system but in
theal System Theory the dyamics are
pregiven through the flow function
feal system system AAL System Theory
system is a specific deterministic flow
so you can't change the flow through
time so you can't model the construction
of new constraints and you can't model
the emergence of new parameters that
affect caal your system so the FP in of
itself cannot present the creative
evolution of either cognitive kinds so
such as money shares or soci
constraints
and this is where we have to get in
weirder uh spaces formally to get
something that looks like could model
openend Evolution although I cannot say
definitively it can because we didn't
yet by construction when we work with
set theory which is the basic theory of
mathematics which is about specific
objects that are purified we can't have
what kofman calls adjustment possible
which correspond to new evolutionary
possibilities that are brought about by
the evolution evolution of evolutionary
system like living
systems um simply set theory forces you
to Define all of the possibilities at
step one of the modeling process so
can't have your system that builds new
possibilities with activity this is not
a coherent Concept in set theory however
what we can do is to look at rather than
set theory at a category Theory which is
let us say another approach to
mathematic which looks not at specific
objects and their relationship through
functions but have specific spaces and
the relationships through
functors and this change in approach
basically does not entail at least not a
Priory that when you write a system you
have to write all of the possibilities
that are within the system preemptively
you can write to space and then look at
the relationship uh between the space
and other adjacent spaces that could
correspond to adjacent
posses and one thing that is related to
that at least in spirits is uh I won't
get into detail but formal approaches
that allow you to build Quantum State
spaces from the property of quantum
obser a rather than the opposite so
simply speaking we can look at the
problem of uh how cognition brings about
new possible not as a space of
possibilities in which there is a flow
but as a set of spaces in which specific
events uh such as observation such as
enculturation such as invention of New
Concept can bring about new
spaces and when we rewrite activity
difference in the language of category
Theory we get things that are uh that do
not quite say the same thing as demal
System Theory like actual active
inference actual FY
principle uh but we get things that are
very very complicated so the diagram
that you see on the bottom left of the
screen is a con cocon diagram I could
tell you what the conon diagram is but I
don't know so I could not explain that
is meant to present the alignment in
reference frame
or the mutual active inference between
two
subsystem so again formally we have no
reason to believe this can't model and
evolution but also given the level of
absess of the math we have very very few
grip with which to understand what we're
looking at and how this relate to
specific cognitive and cultural
processes so there is a lot of progress
to be made in that direction before we
have a self standing theory of openend
cultural
Evolution uh and uh the basic handle of
C constraints I think is a good bridge
between the very concrete very simple
deal System Theory and the Very abstract
um problem of M Evolution so let us wrap
this up here and uh try to take out a
few Snippets of actionable information
that was included in the
talk uh first agents
by Nature they engage with the world
with their world as a cognitive
landscape that is defined by the
modalities by which they perceive the
world that is defined by the intr
Nativity that the agent experience and
that
is again sorry just
back 22
seconds but still the audio is not ready
yet but it's okay we'll breathe before
we jump into the
conclusion
okay I still don't hear
you
no we can do the slide game where
someone else presents the slide
any volunteers okay yeah I heard
that okay cool can please continue okay
we'll try to go fast because this is not
agreeable uh so one agents engage with
the wall as a cognitive landscape which
is defined by our forenses so minimal
presentation of the action that are
possible in the landscape and the
normativity that's embedded in the
possibility of the action two uh the
fact that humans collectively enact
relatively coherent Str cultural
landscape it entails that we have social
constraints over Collective Behavior and
the existence of those soci constraints
they enable Al thought do not
necessitate the emergence of higher
scale agencies such as institution
organization and maybe Godlike
beings and uh last the damic of
constraints they entail a duality
between the creation of meaning so the
way we human
uh create a way to understand the world
and the construction of physical
possibilities posses in the sense
specific concrete causally relevant
possibilities uh that characterize a
specific social cultural organizations
and maybe like physical obervation
pareses but just not worry about it and
all of it is embedded in this diagram
the engagement and the uality with a
system of constraints that produce
itself in a manner so a claim that I'm
making on the record here is that if we
understand correctly every arrow in this
diagram we understand cure Evolution we
understand what human are and we
understand evolution in the cultural
world and here I'll go through the
slides in case someone needs a reference
and has the time to you know go through
the video to find the
reference so thank you and sorry about
the audio
thing
did did this go
well yes it gave some much needed
silences so it was all good um cool
well first ma or Maria if you would like
to give any comments or or Reflections
otherwise we can go to a few topics and
then talk about how we want to conclude
with the
course but first Ma Maria do you want to
say or ask
anything um no I mean this was a great
summary uh I think you covered a lot of
grounds I think uh ideally I would have
liked to see
[Music]
um how much we can do with Gauge
Theory and how this can uh potentially
link us to
to
uh and understandings of power I think
that would be uh that would be
interesting cool thank you
Maria all right see you
Maria okay anyone in live chat can ask a
question or
um let's first address the the course
question while people are writing
questions live chat so what what do you
see for the coming weeks as we kind of
conclude this first
round uh so um you're asking me
right so uh for a reason I do not
understand and Danielle do understands
uh no one came up at the M discussion
session so I thought it would be
interesting to uh like push the for the
last session to have you know everyone
saying their things have feedback and uh
I have a current thing uh to move on
from uh the question is whether you need
you feel there is a need for a
discussion that is specific for the
session we have we have had just now
because lots of thing were covered lots
of audio problems were
existing and basically the two options
are either next session is everyone
present uh we give you feedback ch
or we have a discussion session so at
the time that was initially planned for
the conclusion and then we have yet
another session that will be the
conclusion where you will make the
presentation and you will get the
feedback so we'd like to know which is
your preference because all both are
very possible in my book like doesn't
change anything to me so what you want
is
goes yeah now also open to your thoughts
and of course we're sharing it so that
people can write in live chat or let us
know in the coming days what they prefer
I'm down for a discussion of what we
covered here the slides being linked and
going into some of these next steps and
then a form based registration for a
presentation only session so that we'll
then know exactly who wants to present
what and we'll then we can ask how many
minutes they want to do or something
like that but
ma uh yeah I think uh it would be good
to get people who are interested in
getting more active
to um to come and make a small
presentation uh explain what they
understood uh dis describe the
highlights for them and potentially link
it to some Topic in social sciences we
may not have covered here uh but that
they now see through a different lens I
think that would be
interesting
okay all right I will uh look through
the live chat while I was getting some
water and then we'll ask any questions
that people come up
with is there ever symmetric information
between or among social
entities or maybe from the scripts
perspective ma or from the or however
it's you see it in relation with the
constraints I mean what about asymmetric
constraints I'm not sure understand the
question can the person give a little
more detail in terms in the question
okay um's back but uh there was a
question in the chat about um are in can
information ever be symmetric you talked
about symmetries so are those symmetries
in the information that two social
entities have or are they in the
constraints that entities
experience but what are the symmetries
and what are the
breaks I would say that depend in which
space you model the
problem an information it
entails uh symmetry because it has to be
readable so you have to be a
conservation between uh context or time
of something that is considered to be
the content of the information bearing
thing uh but also it is a symmetry
breaking because uh if you take any like
uh presentation format let us say binary
a random string means nothing and you
have to break the symmetry of the UN
distribution to say something so like it
depends very heavily on how specifically
you are modeling the problem but like
for fundamental reasons any uh
mathematical representation it depends
on the implicit model of the symmetries
of the system because you want to things
that do not matter but you have to
things that do matter and then you have
a very uh uncomfortable amount of
Freedom over how you want to present any
single
thing certainly this comes up in
learning active inference and in talking
about it like what you described how
many ways there are to model a given
thing which is related to which
symmetries are preserved as you
mentioned so H how do we reckon with
that space and with the different ways
of representing the same social
setting so um a reason why I'm not quite
comfortable with the uh notion of
information is that
in all possible settings where I Define
quantum information Theory as not
possible because like very few people
overall think about it information will
be a probability distribution it will be
a like a functional of a probability
suion that is minus to the logarithm of
the probability that is what self
information is
and this is defined over probability
distribution distribution is defined
over State space so implicitly
information entails definition of a
state space so if you want to work over
things that are prior to State spaces
you cannot work with information in like
any coherent definition so
the basically the one thing uh you could
do uh that is vaguely inspired from work
in a Quantum information Theory mainly
by Christopher
first is to not look at the probability
but at the um sorry not to look at the
information I'm using that term in a
cial way now because I have to switch
meaning uh defination not as a property
of the distribution but a property of
quantum operator that corresponds to
observation and that embeds basically we
could say again in a very very
colloquial sense something akin to an
expectation or a
measurement uh or a synchronization
event in the active inference model and
this for a specific type of
operator uh for a specific type of
spaces you can get basically the space
that flows from the operator rather than
the other way around and then
information
is like it's not kov complexity it's not
shannel information it's not a variant
of entropy it is basically what
hypothesized by the specific operators
that you use to interact with matter and
with cultur and natural environments and
maybe maybe there is a big maybe here I
should say maybe one more time maybe
this Con uped in some way uh to account
for the process of eneration where the
um basically the process ination is
considered as the integration of
specific reference frames like
expectation cially
and this entail the evolution of a
cognitive landscape and our social
constraints either defined over the
cognitive landscape or defined as a
self-standing mathematical object I do
not
know uh but if we have that and if we
have a decent level of understanding of
what constraints the evolution of neur
frames we have a self sending theory of
the unfolding of ctive Landscapes and of
openend culture Evolution this is a
sufficient condition I am sure of that
but it is very very hard to reach
like
I there are so many threats by which you
could take it and each one is a like the
level of post do in mathematics and I'm
not talking about 19th century
mathematics not talking about algebraic
topology I'm talking about weird
category thing that people only figured
out how to define 30 years ago so yeah
I'm not confident I will give you an
answer to that within five years I'm not
confident wow very interesting there all
right some questions from the chat so
first upcycle Club wrote do you think
ritualized storytelling is driven by
social
constraints everything is uh driven by
cir constraints we just Define cir
constraints as the Contra that exist
over behavior um
if we expect that every night we have to
go around the fire uh and listen to
someone tell a story then yeah like this
will happen if we expect that we have to
go on YouTube and listen to talks about
abstract things such as inference this
will happen so in this sense everything
every single activity you have is
embedded in a landscape of expectation
and this is why it's pretty hard to talk
about basic mechanism of transmission
because which whichever cognitive
mechanism you are looking at is
encultured and could in principle and
likely has been a few times uh chall M
to
Evolution so um
yes cool and that takes me back to the
scripts discussion in papers the strong
script at exactly this time here's the
script that we're all going to read from
on through the spaces of weaker script
like we tend to meet here or there
happens to be a path here okay so then
some comments from M
lenin1 thank you I don't know if making
a presentation to explain what one
understood is an attractive invitation
still two places I did not track as well
as I hope was one dissolution of agency
as we know it and two the informational
geometry among agent environment and
Boundary went over my head thank
you so dissolution of agency and um
agent environment
boundary yes I will get back to the
slides um are you seeing the
window yeah I'll I'll I'll bring it in
that's fine thank
you okay no no
so uh the dissolution of agency is um
basically the idea
that when we when we think about agents
people like we think as a system that as
a body and that has a brain and that has
the ability for discursion like
deliberating over what you do and not do
and we place agency at the level of disc
discursive beliefs so if I say um I want
to grab the water and I grab the water I
grab the water out of my agency if I
inadv like I don't know bump into
something and make it fall or grab
without thinking about it is it agentive
uh not most people would say yes but
that's actually not inail by the most
used model of agency like legally
speaking you are held as uh not
responsible of less or less responsible
of things that you did not have the
opportunity to debate over
but from a purely cognitive perspective
and if the inference model is correct
the uh bulk of the intentionality of
your ability to direct your own flow
that you have does not come from
reasoning and
deliberation and uh Central executive
system like cognitive function that we
associate with reasoning and agency it
is it comes from the basic expectation
you have yourself and the world because
your expectation over the world uh
constraint heavily implicate the
opportunities for Action that you
perceive and your beliefs or yourself
constrain just as heavily um the options
that you will end up
pursuing and so the agency your ability
to decide of stuff it mostly reduces to
practive process over your self model
and your Ro model and this is while not
like I I don't see any problem formally
of or empirically with that picture like
as I understand it accounts very well
for for the for the um neuros
psychiatric and like psychological
literator and sociological literator
like this is good this works
scientifically but this is cont inuitive
because again most people would expect
you to have reasoning and then to deci
side of stuff and then to execute of all
the stuff you decide which again I don't
think this happens so
harder question is the information
geometry I kind of gloss over it
because
yeah so uh the information geometry is a
geometry that is defined within AAL
system equipped with the partition blah
blah blah and so by a geometry uh I mean
basically a space uh of curvature that
exist over your bzel space this is
basically the same thing that I'm
presenting
in the um uh bottom left of the screen
here you have a space that is your
normal space where you see stuff happen
which is represented here by the line
and you have a curvature that is defined
by some of the things that are defined
over the space and by the freny
principle uh when you have this
partition condition that is verified
then uh each space uh it's sorry each
state in the agent internal uh States
like each specific point it can be
corresponds to a belief distribution
over the um states of the
environments and so this is in this
sense that we have an information
geometry like we have a geometry so
curator over space where the space is
the internal state of the agent and the
geometry is belief over exal
States and uh furthermore this matters
because uh the agent like is actually
constrained by
the the agent is uh effectively
constrained by the by the geometry in
such a way that it inter its internal
flow uh optimizes the Bas and coherence
of the belief that exists according to
the
geometry So This is
highly this is math this is like
straightforward but lots of words lots
of rection no real visual AG put it so
this is more something to like read
about and something to hear about which
is why I gloss over it but I hope going
over it again brings a bit more of
clarity how would you connect what you
just said to the differences with
written and oral culture like what is
hearable what is
seeable How does
writing in the printed or etched or
digitized
form relate to how you discussed culture
today uh I I see you as Frozen Danielle
can you hear
me I can hear you Ma
okay so do answer or do ma answer you
want yeah please I can give a little bit
of an idea but effectively we're talking
about precision and temporality right so
writing and uh
discourse the discourse has to relate to
pragmatics and the the discourse is
likely to be interpreted because it has
lower Precision than say writing has
over time um so here you're talking
about the ways in which the information
geometry will be bent and shifted
through the Precision of the
embedded um of the embedded normativity
that is given rise to uh through these
um through these markers that you can
point to over and over and over with
high Precision I think that's the
link yeah basically that uh so when I
talk about Ro taking and language I
claim that the core reason why this
matter is because this enforce coherence
between the cognitive landscape
experienced by agents and writing
changes massively the scale I which it
is possible and it changes massively the
level of emotional embedment of the uh
of the of language it is much lower in
speech than sorry much higher in speech
uh than it is in uh writing especially
if you account for like singing as a
form of speech uh so
historically
writing very very clearly and very
Ambiguously powered the rise of
administration so States so organization
that uh do a lot of accounting and
bookkeeping like book is literally in
the word and that enable the
centralization of resource
management uh this is explained in
detail in uh the logic of writing by
goody g o o d y
and
yeah basically this writing is a core
cultural Innovation that enabl
centralized policies city states things
like
that yeah that's very
interesting so one topic out all that
we've discussed and maybe you could
unpack a little bit here is thinking of
culture and these cognitive
ecosystems leads to consideration of the
cognitive security or of different
information risk aspects so where does
that come into play with the formalism
or what you discussed
here so uh from a cognitive security
aspect one thing you can uh read in
formalism quite directly is that if you
control the environment as in the
cognitive landscape experienced by agent
you control what the agent do uh
directly
so
there two things that are very very very
um stereotypically ass cognitive
security this is uh Russian uh
propaganda not quite propaganda
cognitive Warfare campaigns pretty much
around the world uh more generally the
um propaganda that is used by
authoritarian regimes to get stuff going
and the
um uh Cults yeah cults that uh
historically are uh tied to the worry of
brain control by evil CS that can
control you from a far like you had a
you know
telecommand and so in both cases um
actually let us get back a bit when you
are a state that does propaganda uh
and like when you a state you can do a
lot of materal engineering so producing
the Environmental uh states of the um in
which people live in and uh for example
if you look at the city of Brazilia
which is uh one of the uh very few uh
spe specifically built capital city that
exist in the world there is like one in
there's Brazilia and there is like I
think maybe four others and those cities
are basically very big glorified
administrative
centers and brazilan in particular it
does um neighborhoods for work
neighborhoods for ler neighborhoods for
um for habitation it is
extremely uh divided and because of this
dividedness you basically don't get to
do stuff that are not work or hang out
with your family that is not a
possibility and of course this Chang
massively the way people experience
their life and this trans massively the
topology of thisal network that can
emerge
uh but when you are doing cognitive
Warfare like in the sense that NATO
defines so you are state or state
lonization and you are trying to
with another state or state oranization
you don't get to just build cities that
are bad but is not possibility that you
have so what the um Russian do in a
systematic way is to try to basically
create doubts over what information is
reliable so that people feel paralyzed
uh the target I must insist critically
is not the information that is available
it is TR that people can have the
actionability that the people can give
to the information and so I tend to
propagate a lot of conspiracy theory
nonsense because it occupies a lot of
space and it prevents the possibility
for public debates to occur and another
strategy they use is to manipulate the
personal identity uh that are embedded
often in ethnicity or uh in the case of
the US of advanced countries that have
uh where political life is mostly
decoupled for for ethnicity and I
understand the irony to say that this is
the case in the US but you don't have
like ethnic ethnically specific parties
are armed forces so this is less the
case that elsewhere so in these
countries they will use political
identity so they will use Republican
identity uh or leftist identity but
mostly replicant identity to like just
push complete nonsense and get people to
act in a way that overall dis stabilize
the grip of the us over uh their own
population and so this is the
basic
uh way that we do cognitive Warfare and
you can understand this in terms of
social constraints because again the
target is not like information of itself
it's the it's the possibility that is
afforded by the social context in which
you evolve at turn incent the goal is to
create uh doubt and noise in the public
setting is trate constraints that are
not compatible with a efficient
Collective
organization and a way like a way where
you do it is um when you see it being
done in a much more systematic and
efficient way is of course uh with
intrastate influence where State
administrator and state institutions
they try to create grip over a
population and if you look at the birth
of nationalism uh like we have the
notion today that nations are somewhat
coherent political group that let us say
the French hang out together and take
theion together uh this
notion it's not quite recent streetly
speaking but the fact that is dominant
that it is just a St expectation is very
recent and it's it derives from the
French uh that somehow where a group of
administrator somehow managed to
convince everyone that they shared uh
identity and they shared Mutual
obligation responsibility in virtue of
this
identity and uh the way in which this
happens is they sent uh instituts in
villages and they sent soldiers and you
had to listen the the children had to
listen to the inors explained to them
that they were French and they needed to
do French things like going to war for
friends and if you did not let the
children uh like do that it you went to
prison and no one wants to go to prison
so with of course I am a I'm doing a
very very huge caricature here this like
there is not a shadowy set of influence
that
sense this is a over specification but
what happen is that the fren State
managed to create a social Niche up in a
very very forign bra Villages where um
French Hood became a basic condition of
existence most of your social thing the
fact that you were legally recognized as
existing uh the activities activity that
you had lot of those were embedded in
your perception of being French and so
when this is the case and when you see
that Administration is tends to be on
top of things thetion tells you you have
to go to war in virtue of freshness then
you go to war don't like fight against
the administration you fight against
whoever Mission tells you uh fact that
you have agreed implicitly that you are
French befor hands makes this lot lot
harder to resist basically than if like
let's say just uh send solar at you and
kidnapped you and give you a swear until
you fight this this is not how you make
things efficient uh Army this way are un
organized they are un motivated they are
not good and if you want people to have
Stakes uh you need to give them power or
you need to give them the impression
they have power because they are French
and here French uh like govern things
and whether you are in the set of French
that actually direct things or
not bad question to ask just you know go
to the
trenches and this type of uh things we
would not think as cognitive Warfare
because we would not think as a like it
as a
between like implicitly when we talk
about Warfare we talk between states or
between Nation conflict and this is
within a nation within AAL group but you
can look at um
Cults and how they create social
influence uh you can look at for example
one of the most famous Cults that
existed which is the monies or the
unification
Church um they were widely accused to
make uh brainwashing they were the
accused to somehow control people and
make them do things they don't want to
do that is not possibility you are ation
like you cannot kidnap people and hope
that it will be okay you will get killed
by police if you do that most likely in
the US in this specific um uh space
where the ination church evolved what
you can do is to create a context where
you have a huge grip over what you what
people can and cannot say what they can
and can think about themselves you can
tell them that uh Your Leader is the uh
coming of Jesus that uh is going to
bring everyone in paradise and you can
make people go to a work session to talk
about it and you can just like
physically cling to those people all the
time until you are quite confident that
they feel that whatever you are doing is
important and you can have very big
emotional ritual where everyone like uh
cries and become extremely embedded in
the uh group ership and who can be
extremely supportive of group members uh
while being extremely
like aggressive to anything
that go away from group identity and
when you Pro this environment and people
Eng in this environment for a long time
right time to develop this group
identity so when you tell them uh the
big leader tells you to give us 2,000
Euros uh sorry
20,000 20,000 Euros for your ancestors
not to go to uh
hell that seems reasonable that seems
like a reasonable ask which it would not
unless you had a very tight control over
uh the social environment of someone
because then it's not just giving money
uh in exchange for good this is about
upholding your self identity as someone
who follows and believes the C
stitching so and yet again this is
something that is formalized directly in
terms of s constraints because this is
about what you can and cannot do in a
given text this is not
about like abstract belief it's not
about brain control it's not about
anything but what you can cannot do in a
given social
context all right there was a ton there
let me let me kind of retrace a few of
the pieces that that I heard there so
towards framing cognitive security under
this cognitive constraint framework that
you're discussing for which active
inference under the free energy
principle is the process theory that
gets it done first you described how
modern states have a lot of
administrative capacity and affordances
especially through writing and
especially again in the last decades and
centuries of information environment
changes and then you pointed to two kind
of patterns or genres or motifs of
influence or cognitive Warfare
propaganda and Cults discussed one
example of them surely could have gone
into more detail or there's other
examples and perspectives and so on and
um as ma alluded to earlier Precision
modulation is a key aspect of constraint
I mean Precision modulation of how
tightly you're holding the baseball bat
is Rel the movement its Precision in
wobble is going to be related to the to
the grasp and so
um increasing uncertainty can lead to
anxiety and doubt all of that's very
wrapped up in a narrative setting then
you discussed how there's a ratcheting
of thinking and acting like a state
breaking symmetries like states do and
getting grasp over the subject over the
citizen that's a complex topic but
that's what you went and then there are
asymmetries
around control of the environment the
information environment ability to to
read write edit in the information
environment and that leads to these uh
engineered distributions of what is
important or what means what which
justifies or even writes the blank check
for requests of funds whatever the
narrative is around those funds um but
more fundamentally those strategies can
threaten sens making which is to say the
inbound perceptual component of AC of
inference and then also decision making
and action selection which is the
fundamental complement the outbound
aspect of active
inference I'll read another comment from
live oh yeah do you want to add anything
else on that get uh like I'd like to
point out a very very specific example
that is
contemporary uh which is the
um uh like the campaign by Israel to
remove people from the Gaza bands uh so
just I don't know when people will watch
it so on the 7th of October 11 days ago
Hamas which is a terrorist organization
islamist oranization that is dominant in
the Gaza band attacked Israeli and
slaughtered IR settlers that were nearby
and slaughtered tourists that were
nearby and attacked military bases they
made I think 2,000
deaths and uh so the state of Israel has
a cont that is currently um led by very
far right parties things that we would
not have equivalent in of in Europe or
the US has decided to answer by uh like
blaming each indidual Palestinian for
this and trying to uh like Deport them
elsewhere and uh so like this this is
not itself what I'm trying to comment
about what I'm trying to comment about
is that
every single comment you will see about
it on Twitter makes the confusion
between Hamas and pales on one side and
IDF nanu and the israelian on the other
side and so this produce of framing that
says basically um people are not people
are trying to decide whether the amas
action are jifi or not and implicitly in
this debate they create a context where
whoever lose uh whichever uh group lose
the Legacy debate gets to be killed to
the last
and so you that produce very very um
basically that produce a framing that uh
makes the only possibility in the
conflict examination because each side
uh like there is no like this is not two
side dyamic there is not Palestinian
Land There is the uh the Israel land
there is the um I will not make all the
relation but by this framing uh like the
framing that either the Arabs or the Jew
must Prevail and kill the other you give
a lot of power for groups to just make
this a genocidal war and justify things
like cutting water to one million people
because uh like 200 of them uh committed
a
massacre and like I do not know if there
is a single actor that tried to get this
I do not think this is the case but this
is a very powerful instance of how proa
does not need to Target what you believe
but it does need to Target how you frame
problems yeah lot to say on that
any last pieces you want to
discuss uh no it is
good I have talked a lot I'd like to
stop
talking
okay well thank you we will um send out
updates to people about the coming
weeks so thank you all right bye ciao
thank for thanks for your
attention
goodbye